You can delegate your work to AI.
You can’t delegate your responsibility to AI.
Your company cannot delegate the reputation to AI.
Your company's reputation is their responsibility.
I wake up every morning, I ask a few questions in my head Ethics.
Integrity. My responsibility.
What do I sign my name on?
If I don't take that as a responsibility for myself, if I work for a company
where they don't care, I think we are in a bigger risk overall.
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for developers
and engineering leads at the cutting edge of AI and agenetic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple., every week
as we chat with the most exciting voices in AI and tackle
the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
Back in November, we hosted
the first ever in-person AI native dev con in New York.
This June 1st and second, we're bringing it to London.
It's two days built for AI-native developers and engineering teams, one day
full of hands on workshops and one day full of practical talks on
agent skills, context engineering, agent orchestration and enablement platforms
and how teams are actually shipping AI in production.
Join us at the Brewery in London near the Barbican for all of that,
plus networking parties, giveaways and a room full of people.
Building the future of AI native development.
You can also join us from anywhere in the world via the live stream.
As you're listening to this podcast.
You get 30% off your ticket with Code Pod 30.
Just head to ainativedev.io and we'll see you in London.
Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI Native Dev Podcast.
And we are here in Austin live at Arc of AI.
And joining me is the wonderful Venkat Subramaniam.
And Venkat is one of the co-creators of this conference.
Venkat a massive welcome.
How are you doing? Great.
Yeah, I love Austin.
Yeah, I love food, I love people, Austin is the place to come for good
barbecue, good food. Right?
Right.
And I love technology.
Yeah, and having them all in one place.
And Venkat, you are by day.
You are an incredible author.
You're a wonderful teacher, both as a professor
but also at incredible conferences just like this and around the world.
You teach courses, you inspire people to learn about programing
and now a lot about AI, right?
How do you find the time number one.
Thank goodness.
There's 24 hours in a day.
Imagine imagine if there were only 23.
Let's talk a little bit about Arc of AI.
First Arc of AI.
What does it mean?
Arc of AI yeah.
So so with all the excitement around AI happening,
we were sitting around talking among friends and the question was,
how do we really bring some sense and discipline
and practice into this noise that we hear around us?
And, and one of the things that we are very fortunate collectively,
I'm saying, is that we have a community of developers who are not only
really good in development, but who are good in speaking as well.
So the thought was, what if we bring those developers
to form a conference that's focused on AI, but we don't want this
to be an AI by the marketing of the large organizations.
That's one of the reasons why the speakers in this conference are practitioners,
and not from the AI companies that are trying to sell you a product
that makes a huge difference in terms of the content they bring,
because they are talking about how do we use this rather than
what can we sell you? Yes.
And so then the question is there is no.
We often talk about a narrative arc, and
there is a trajectory through which we go through as a technology curve.
I've been programing for about 40 years when I was a young kid.
If I can say that as a young kid, there was this thing called object
oriented programing in the distance, and then we saw people
complaining about it being really, you know, anxious about it.
And then the dust settled.
We started using object-oriented programming.
It became a foregone conclusion that we would be building with a.
And then you see this kind of a curve that happens for every single technology.
And there's nothing we do that doesn't go through that curve.
So. So with that in mind,
my thought was we're going to go through the same curve for AI as well.
So hence the arc. Of AI.
And where would you say we are on that arc
somewhere.
Still on the climb.
Yeah I think we're still in a lot of hype cycle.
But at the same time, I also think that we are also beginning
to make sense of what works and what doesn't work.
And I'm not trying to place you up on this,
but really, that's one of the things I've heard from people here
is where they enjoyed the keynote that un yesterday,
where you are really providing that cautionary tone
as to there is power here, but we need to bring that.
The word I would summarize your keynote is to me
this is an important word.
Is the word discipline right?
To me the problem in software is not we don't have a technology.
We have a lot of it.
The problem is not that we don't have people.
We have a lot of good people.
The problem is we don't have enough discipline.
And not that we don't have discipline because we are,
you know, unorganized or, you know, negligent.
We don't have discipline because there is so much pressure
that takes focus away from discipline.
And then it comes and bites us in the back.
And that's when we begin to realize, okay, let's slow.
Down. And see.
You know, it's kind of like driving, right?
You can drive fast, but if you are a disciplined driver,
you don't get there fast.
But you also you also get there safer.
And that's kind of what these messages are, including the keynote
in a lot of other talks is how do you bring the discipline into what we do.
So so I think we are in the face of the curve where we have
we have launched, but now we are thinking about sustainability.
We are thinking about how can we get results from this
rather than solid dimension, this curve
being like a spacecraft that crashes back on Earth.
But to be able to launch really and succeed.
And it's interesting because AI,
one of the great benefits of AI is the speed it gives us in terms of
I can either create things faster than I would without AI,
but also maybe even when I'm sleeping or when I'm, you know, when an agent
can kind of like run in the distance while I'm doing other things.
But it's it's not just about can you do something quicker?
It's about can I do something quicker, but also have that discipline
to be able to say, you know what, I still want to slow it down a little bit
by adding those precautions, that safety in making sure
we still have that CI/CD processes, because that's what as software
engineers, we know, these are the safety nets that we require
to actually be able to deliver and produce solid production level code.
Absolutely.
Somebody said this to me and I was like, you know,
that's the way I never thought about it before, but but they said,
you got to break in a car so you can go faster.
Yeah.
And discipline actually makes you go faster.
And I think to your point, right, to bringing in CI/CD to bring in reviews,
to bring in those stage gates, to say I am confident
that where we got in right now is good enough to go to the next stage
and to be able to have control of where we are
taking this forward with the speed, that agility,
with the with the speed that AI gives us and the discipline we bring,
so that it's kind of like, you know, the homeless diseases, right?
So you don't want to tilt in one direction and you lose the center of gravity.
So maybe the speed of AI
and the discipline we bring stabilizes and gives us that center of gravity.
So, so we are able to stabilize and move forward
rather than go haywire in one direction or the other.
I think we will take time to learn more of those.
And honestly, between last year
when we ran this conference and this year, I have to tell you
that I'm noticing two things very significantly.
The topics are a lot more mature,
and also that developers
are a lot more curious and interactive.
I felt like last year they were in Let Me Listen more,
but this year they are more fun.
Interactive mode.
I've been sitting in a few talks, you know, whenever I'm able to do.
And one of the things I am absolutely enjoying, in addition
to the presenter giving the talk, is the questions that people are asking.
Yeah.
And that says that
they're not just listening, they're bringing their current experience,
and then either they're validating or they are refining
which which is really the reason for us to be here.
And I think that that's the that's where the curve is, is that we are going
to the next phase or an exchange in this where we are going beyond.
Let me find out what it is to let me see how I can apply it.
That really resonates, actually, because a number of the questions
and discussions that I had, people were taking the topic and going,
okay, this is how I'm using AR, I'm using windsurf, can I use this with windsurf?
And they're actually trying to
they're trying to work out what they can take, the gems that they can take.
And how do I apply that into my existing environment.
What does it replace. What can I use it with.
And so that's a really interesting observation. I've definitely.
And even in the hallway, what blew my mind is, you know, as I was walking,
somebody said, hey, hang on a second.
I got a question for you. Yeah.
And then the question rolls into, this is what we are
doing at work, and I'm trying to scale what we are doing.
Yeah. How would you approach it?
And that's heartwarming because people are really engaging
to learn, which is the whole point of being here.
Right?
And I can see that energy
in people taking the time to go deeper.
And they're eager. I can see it.
They are eager to take that back and apply it on.
I bet some of these people are going to go back to work on Friday.
Yeah, they're not going to take the weekend. Long weekend.
And that's exactly the reason to be here.
I'm seeing that energy. Amazing.
AI stands for artificial intelligence.
But I know that's not new to.
You. Know.
But you call it accelerated inference. Yes.
Tell us what the distinction is and how someone,
a developer should mindfully know the difference.
So I think this is this is one thing that I at least
helped me in working with AI.
So to me, an artificial intelligence
elevates it to something of a,
you know, a being that that I should respect and listen to.
And again, you know, not that I'm disrespectful about,
you know, lifeless things.
I'm not disrespect to this so far. Right.
I'm not going to put my foot on it.
But but the point is
an intelligent being to me, it deserves a higher level of respect.
Yeah, artificial intelligence is too much of a respected, respectful term for me.
and I would accept it if that's what it was in my mind.
But but to me, if I if I tell you, if you look around here.
Right. And if I tell you.
Oh, look, that person is wearing a full sleeve shirt.
Oh, so does the person next to.
Oh, there's the third person with the full sleeve.
Oh, there's a fourth person which would sleep.
And I ask you,
what do people where are you going to say, gosh, they wear food sleeve.
So in other words, Inference is neither right or wrong.
But inference is based on the data that's available for us.
The programmers code is the data, right?
Well, the problem is not that AI has not been trained.
The problem is a has been trained a. Lot.
On a lot of code.
And I don't think you need to really convince any human
to, you know, say do humans in general.
You know, overall every single human put together,
do we write really good code or we write terrible code?
I think most of us will agree.
We write terrible code as humans. We have done that.
And the reason is we have really struggled to write high quality code.
But AI has been trained on that vastness of code.
So when you ask it to infer, it doesn't know to infer
from the good parts and leave out the bad parts.
So the inference is cumulative on everything it's seen.
So this is one of the reasons why you see a generic code.
It generates either code that doesn't compile or doesn't work
properly, or the code appears broken.
And why?
Because the phrase I want to use is look what the dog just dragged in.
Yeah, well, it's
not that you like what it dragged in, but that's what it found in the backyard.
Yeah.
So so I think that's why I call it an inference engine.
It's an accelerated inference.
You and I in for a lot.
But our capability to infer is limited not by our
availability of data, but our ability to consume that information.
We only can hold so much at a time.
So machines will always be faster than humans.
That's where the acceleration comes in.
And so it's an accelerated inference engine.
We are just maybe a little bit more of a refined but slower inference.
You know, I wouldn't call ourselves an engine but capable to infer in that
regard.
So to me, AI stands for “Accelerated Inference.”
and not as much an acceleration artificial intelligence.
And I want to I want to focus down on that piece that you mentioned whereby
as a as a community, perhaps our code, our coding isn't the best time, probably,
you know, a good example of maybe some of the worst bits in that,
in that, in that community code. Yeah.
But ultimately when we get bad code from AI,
I think you have to it in the past as this is karma,
this is like the years of our bad code that we are providing.
We're getting it back now.
So I guess, what does that tell us about, I guess, number one,
the state of the industry, but to how we as developers
should think about the output of of the code from a, from an AI agent.
Right. And what we need to do about that.
Yeah.
So, so
so there are two issues here that I think we need to be really careful about.
The software industry is not as mature
as a as a construction industry, for example.
Right.
Humans have been building, you know, structures where we live, right?
Where we decide for for centuries.
If I'm building a house, I can't just grab somebody
out of the street and say, build this house for me.
The county will not allow that to happen.
The county sends inspectors.
They inspect multiple places multiple times.
The reason is there is there's a concern of loss of life.
If a beam here, right there, sitting this beautiful building.
But if the beam above you were to fall, that's that's extremely risky.
And so to me, there are consequences to what we do, the software industry,
because it's
relatively new and it's been accelerating.
We've been enjoying a lot more lenient.
C right.
But that's that's going to expire when it becomes to expire.
Unfortunately it's the it's the lawyers that's going to be stepping in.
Because when, when when lawsuits emerge that's when we begin to pay attention.
And and so what are we.
What have we done so far?
Even though the quality of code we write as humans is not correct,
we typically balance it out on teams where people can create things.
But then there are other team members who constantly
review them and also rework and refactor.
So one of the things we have been doing for the past about 20 years
is we write code, but we continuously refactor code.
Why are we doing factoring code?
Because the code we wrote, not because entirely of our fault.
A lot of times we don't know where we are going,
and so when we get clarity on it, we have to rework the code.
We refactor it.
So so that's how we've been coping with that.
But but in that regard, the speed at which humans are able to write code
is in pace with the speed at which humans are able to review code.
Yeah, but when the speed of generating code increases and the ability
for us to review is still the same, I think we're in bigger trouble.
Yeah.
And that's where we need better tools to review the code as well.
So the maturity in this regard has to be that
we as humans still need to take the responsibility.
I cannot tell my company, don't ask me
to take responsibility anymore because I've delegated this to AI.
You can delegate your work to AI.
You can’t delegate your responsibility to AI.
Your company can delegate work to AI.
Your company cannot delegate delegate the reputation to AI.
Your company's reputation is their responsibility.
So? So we can we.
So the question is, how can we delegate effort
without throwing our hands up and saying, I'm not responsible anymore, right.
And if we don't, there are consequences to it.
This is where I was talking about what are the things businesses
have to really think about is not the speed at which we can go.
Speed is important, not the speed at which we can go, not the money we can save.
But what is the cost of failure? Yeah.
And if I don't understand the cost of failure for what I produce,
then I'm going to have to face that consequence later on,
and it's not going to be pleasant.
I've had without AI, I have, I have clients that I
that I have directly worked with where
they have been in lawsuits
because of poor quality software they are created.
Personally, I have served on three lawsuits
so far where I've served as an expert witness,
a company suing another company because of poor quality software.
They called me up and said, hey, we know that you are an expert in the industry.
You're a third party. No bias
signed this agreement.
We have not told you what to say.
And then they present me the code and they say
evaluate it and present your findings.
And that's what we're going to take, the code of law.
And I'll tell you in one case, it was
unbelievably low effort for me
because all I had to do was go to the organization
that has the library and get the page of dos and don'ts
and show that every do they didn't and every don't.
They did.
And it breaks my heart when I see people do this.
But and I have another client which got sued literally when their CEO
was delivering a talk and and saying, you have messed this up,
and here's a summons to appear on the court.
And when your company's reputation, in addition to money,
is jeopardized by poor quality of what you produce,
your business people are going to be responding differently.
So at that time they come back and say, fix this.
And I think it's our responsibility as to me a programmer,
we are not coders, we are professionals.
I I wake up every morning, I ask a few questions
in my head Ethics.
Integrity.
My responsibility.
Right?
What do I sign my name on?
And I think that is very important.
And If I don't take that as a responsibility for myself,
and if I work for a company
where they don't care, I think we are in a bigger risk overall.
And that's not what we are here for, I think.
And I think you mentioned a couple of things that including code
reviews and using tools to perform those code reviews.
We can, of course use AI as well to review the code.
And it's our job.
You know, we need to take that output and actually look at the code as well.
Use our judgment.
One thing that you mentioned was this
this interesting inversion where
junior developers or less experienced developers will look at some code
that's been output by AI and they'll go, wow, this is incredible.
It's magic.
And then you look at senior developers who will look at the same output
and they'll hate it.
They'll know what it should do.
They know what they would expect and they can say, this is wrong.
This is wrong. This is terrible. Right?
So there's this gap.
There is that is that almost widening
the gap between a junior and a senior developer,
if they're not necessarily learning, but being exposed?
More to that and assuming
that's the right way, is this widening the gap between between those two types?
It is it is not only widening gap, it certainly is right in the gap.
But I think the risk is even higher.
And to me, one of the one of the biggest challenges
today is if the tools lead us
to turn into consumers of the code.
And in the process, if we lose our critical thinking,
that is a dangerous situation to be in, right?
Because then I'll give you an example of this.
This is, you know, catalogs are great, I love it.
But I'll just give you one example of this.
I was driving one day and we had to
we have to, you know, take care of some payment.
And so the person on the phone said, hey, here's the payment, I've got a discount.
And after the discount are we going to pay this?
And I'm driving I don't have access to any device.
Right.
And I immediately said to the person, I'm sorry, I cannot verify what you said,
but it doesn't sound right.
Could you please run the numbers again one more time and tell me if
after applying discount, it would be this amount?
And there was a pause and then they came back and said, no, you're right.
I had a round of calculation.
Here's the number. I'm like, okay, that makes me feel better.
Yeah.
So so the key here is for me
to process that in my mind and say I'm validating, right?
Yeah, I'm trusting that person.
But at the same time a validating to saying, hey, I'm capable
of making mistakes.
So are you. Let's validate it.
But if I don't think about it critically, we would have sent
a higher amount as a payment and that would have cost other things.
So the key here is at every step,
we need to develop the capability
to check and double check
and say, is this actually correct?
Is this the way we need to do?
And for that
AI can replace our effort, but
AI cannot replace our knowledge. Yes.
I don't have knowledge in chemical engineering.
I can write all the code you want me to write,
but a chemical engineer literally comes down and tells me,
oh Venkat, we never want to do that for hydrocarbons.
And I say, thank you for letting me
know that because I don't have that knowledge.
But an engineer has that knowledge.
But imagine you remove that engineer out of the picture for a minute.
I would be writing the code, which is not going to behave correctly
for a hydrocarbon.
Now replace me with something faster, which is the AI.
And if you don't have that engineer, it's dangerous what you are producing.
So it's not that I was perfect, but the key here is
I had people around me who would do the verification,
and while I write the code, they make sure I'm not writing rubbish.
And in the same way, the person who is using AI,
if it's a senior engineer, senior developer,
they're able to evaluate and say, yeah, that that is good.
Or in this case that's not adequate.
So I'm going to iterate through it a few more times.
It's not like they have to abandon this and do the job by hand, but
they have the smartness in their head to reiterate,
until it gets to where it needs to get to, where's this junior engineer
who never had that benefit to get trained by a senior developer, right?
One of the things I've said in my keynote is something I've been learning
for myself is we study in school, but we learn on the job, right?
In school, we read about stuff, but the real learning happens
when you apply them.
And so when I'm at work, when I'm doing things,
I go to my colleague and say, I'm writing this code this way.
What do you think of this design?
And they critique it for me, and then I do that for somebody else.
And we collectively learn from each other.
And then that's what makes you a senior developer.
To be a senior developer is not an age.
A senior developer is not the number of years you have counted.
The senior developer, to me, is the extent to which you will push back.
The extent to you will challenge ideas in front of you.
Your ability to evaluate and discern between you know you.
If you're a senior developer, you smell the right from the wrong.
You have that auto verve auto validation.
Yeah, that system.
That kind of rise.
That that beef that builds into you.
Yeah.
And, you know,
when I worked with senior developers, as I was, I was a young developer.
That's one thing I would look at and say, you know, from a mile
you are able to identify
this is not going well, right?
You know, I remember
I was working for a company that acquired another company,
and I didn't say this to people because you don't want to insult people.
So I go in and sit down and this is a code I know nothing about, right.
And my boss said, go over there this afternoon, spend some time with them,
because in two months you're going to work with them.
I'm like, okay, so I drive across town.
I'm sitting in this
in this guy's office not knowing anything about the system, right?
And he says, let me show you how things work.
And then he is showing me the screen and he says, oh, hang on a second, banker,
before I can show you this, I got to make a few changes
and he's making some changes.
And I remember right, I would never forget this.
I remember sitting this office and saying,
I don't have a clue what he is doing, but I can tell you he's wrong.
So. So I just said to myself, and I want to insult this person, right?
Because I don't know anything. I have nothing to prove.
Fast forward four months.
I am working on that code and I hit the same spot
and I'm like, heck no, I'm not going to do this.
So I spent two hours because I'm really angry at what
I'm looking at, and I fix this in two hours,
and then the next day he's looking at what I'm doing is like,
oh my gosh, we've been struggling with this.
How in the world did you fix it? And I said, you know what?
I got angry looking at it and I wasted some time.
And here's a solution. I was like, done it.
We never thought you could do this.
And to me, that is the sense, right,
that that going from a junior to maybe a middle of a developer
to to say, I don't know enough about it, but I can tell you it's not right.
And I know it can be improved as a person using AI.
I need to have the sense to say, this is good.
Yeah. Oh, you know what?
This can be improved. Oh, no.
We don't want to go in this direction at all.
No, thanks AI, let's redo this.
And that's interesting because I think one of the things that you
that you mentioned to people is
you don't like one shotting things in AI, and I think you've mentioned to people
try your best not to do that and it becomes more iterative.
Yes, people see that journey and can cause correct more and more, I guess
as models and particular, particularly agents become more capable.
Yes. At what stage do you feel personally and for yourself,
your own use of AI, and also advice that you give other people?
At what stage would you would you be comfortable to think?
Do you know what this is?
Particularly with the agent agent environment?
I'm comfortable with you
going away doing something, and then I'll have a look at what you.
So let me bring in my another definition of AI.
So to
me AI not only stands for accelerated inference,
AI also stands for “agonizingly inconsistent.”
It's agonizingly inconsistent.
And I think at the end of the day,
this is something you mentioned quite a bit in your keynote.
This is the difference between what we
in software development have dealt with until yesterday, so to say.
And the new norm is going from a deterministic word
to a non-deterministic world.
And essentially when you live in a non-deterministic world,
this is it's really a trade off.
Your trade off here is you can go
slower and deterministic or you can go faster and non-deterministic.
You are the determinism is part of the iterations.
You You are the one who brings control to the chaos. Yes.
And you, you You have the speed.
But at the same time you're saying, I I like your speed,
but I need, at the end of the day, still to verify.
and knowing what I know to to answer your question,
at what stage will I be comfortable to say I'm okay with it?
I don't know that yet, because I've been seen enough to
with what exists today to say I'm ready to give that to the AI.
Yeah, so so as far as the things we have so far,
we need to have human in the loop to to do that verification.
We may have we may be doing fewer iterations of verifications
moving forward.
So maybe the answer to your question is when that iteration
distills down to one is when I would have that confidence.
Maybe that's a way to put it.
And do you think that would be models and agents getting better, or
do you think that would be more of kind of like as an environment that we create?
Maybe it's context, maybe it's skills, maybe it's something that can replace,
not replace, but something that we can provide
that will almost be an automated us in the loop where
if it's a school, maybe that says, no, actually,
remember, you need to do it this way or some automated verification.
Do you feel like that's part of a step that's missing?
Yeah.
So so we can learn from other fields in that way, right?
I was talking to a builder recently, and what I love about
people is when they are very open, straightforward, direct.
I really appreciate it.
So the builder said, you want to tell me where to put an electric plug point?
And my answer to you will be yes or no.
And I love it.
And I kind of looked at him and said, not being rude, he said,
when I say yes, I will put the plug point where you want me to put it.
When I say no, it's because the code will not allow me to do it.
And if you tell me no, I'm the one who's paying you do it.
Guess what happens if there's a fire and you don't get sued?
I get. Sued.
Because I'm the one who built it.
And I said, I respect your professionalism here.
So where I'm getting to with this is skills are great, but what if eventually
we can help AI learn
what that skill should be for code generation?
What are the universal do's and don'ts?
What are the things like for example, right.
I think most of us can agree writing
a meaningless singular variable is a terrible thing to do.
I showed some examples during my keynote today.
The variable name was C.
I screamed at my students when they write a variable called C.
I don't think I need a skill to tell AI.
Don't be stupid, right? That should know it.
And so rather than well, skills are great as a as an intermediate step.
Yeah, I cannot imagine five years from now we are sitting in writing skills.
I want AI to not only train, but to be trained on
what are the good practices,
what are the disciplined way and
and if there can be a way to coach AI,
to know the risk, to understand the ways to write code
for it, to know if I write code this way, and if I were to modify this code
in the future to handle something else, it's going to interfere.
And to understand the software is a nonlinear system.
We know this AI needs to also realize it's a non-linear system,
so the actions it takes in one area has impact in another area.
And if AI can be trained to be more vigilant about the risk
it is introducing into software, I think
at that time we will have more maturity and fewer iterations.
I think.
I'd love to hear someone who is very deeply entrenched
in the community,
particularly around this conference, but just generally, you know,
you're talking to a bunch of different individuals, indie developers, as well as
as well as folks in organizations seeing what people are building in in
AI today, what would you say are some of the the biggest problems
that people are building for to improve AI today?
Kind of cutting the hype, cutting through the hype, but actually,
you know, picking the real solutions to the big problems.
What would you say they are today?
They're actually that's one of the interesting part is it is quite vast.
And I'm really happy to see that, you know, for example,
I have seen organizations really
lean into AI for writing automated test.
This is not just saying I'm going to write automated test
for the sake of writing test.
These are real issues.
They are trying to address where they have developed software
for the past ten years, and there are issues.
They're not able to find that defects in the code
because their customers are angry
because these defects are significant, but the team is not able to figure out
because the code is complex and they didn't write the original code,
and they're using AI for writing test so they can have better feedback.
Tools for feedback loops.
The using AI to identify errors,
finding bugs in systems.
You know, you take a code base and say, here's a here's the issue I'm facing.
Can you tell me which area of code I should be able to see it.
In root cause analysis style approach to an issue.
And it's able to pinpoint and say, look over here, right?
This would take months on end for humans to go.
You know, one of the things I'm sure you know, you've seen this quite a bit.
When you hire somebody new, you often put them in QA
and say, learn to fix bugs, because that's when you learn the system.
Then you come to development. Right?
This is a traditional thing that we've seen happen.
But why is that?
Because this gives you
the ability to really go deeper into systems and understand AI.
Your shots are curing that, so you're able to look at defects much more quickly.
I've seen that quite a bit in companies.
You are you are a I'm a consultant.
So I get dragged into companies. I didn't write this code.
I don't even know who they are until I walk into the building
and they are saying, here's an issue, fix it.
And they're using AI to reason about the code
to explain what a piece of code is doing so they can understand better.
They're using AI to refactor code.
They're using AI to evaluate the quality of design.
I know a set of financial organization
that is using AI to create and refine their architecture.
So. So I am looking at an entire vertical in which AI is being used.
I see design engineers use AI,
so so AI is being used just about everywhere.
And I'm seeing this in companies when I walk in, it's a question of
where are you using AI and what's your use case?
And it's it's all over, which is fascinating
and quite scary at the same time.
Yeah, absolutely.
For decades now, Venkat, you've been teaching
expert developers all the way down to junior developers, people going through
universities as well, what it means to be a really good
developer, a solid developer, everything from, you know, agile,
how to do agile well, all the way through to,
you know, development really as a craft with AI. Now,
does this change
things in terms of what it means to be a good developer?
What needs to kind of stay, what is the kind of things that we need
to learn in addition to be a good developer?
Yeah, I love that question because I'll be absolutely honest about it.
There are times you wake up and you doubt yourself, right?
It is important that we doubt ourselves
because otherwise we never improve what we do.
And I'll be honest about it, this was about two months ago.
I've been teaching for 34 years at the university part time, and
and I spent a lot of time with my students I really enjoy.
I like to really help the next generation because I feel like I am where I am
because other people took the time to help me when I was younger.
It's my turn to give back to to the to the next generation.
But I was on a train, you know, in Europe a couple of couple of months ago,
and I was kind of looking at the window just thinking about stuff.
And I asked myself, I've had relevant I'm irrelevant as an instructor
with AI and all the things going on.
Should I just, you know, throw in my towel and say thank you for this?
But I don't need to teach anymore.
The students can learn from me.
And then I realized I'm actually more relevant today than ever.
Sure, I'm teaching them dependency inversion.
Principal fear.
I'm teaching them dry
principal I'm sure I'm teaching them single responsibility principle.
But if you set that aside for a minute,
what I'm really teaching my students and I my my, my
my way of teaching is very different from an orthodox or traditional instruction.
I do code reviews every single day and I, you know,
spend three hours critiquing my students work every day.
And what I'm teaching them is time management and teaching them
when to go deeper and when to park something and come back.
I'm teaching them to push back.
So this semester, for example, right, I gave them a problem
they were solving and a set of students said, why don't we solve it this way?
I said, no, no, no, no, solve it this way.
And they did.
And then a week later, a student came back and said, I don't get it.
Why are you telling me to solve it this way instead of this way?
And I said, explain to me why you say this.
And and he and he came back with the reason I said,
that's why you did not push back.
You just accepted what I said.
And I wanted to wait and see how long you go in the wrong path.
And you came back and pushed back.
And you were one among that many students who pushed back.
And this was a learning experience for all of us.
And and that's what I've been really helping
my students to learn is that aspect, that critical thinking.
So to me, a good developer is not
the one who can, you know, show that they know all the libraries,
all the frameworks, all the things in the world.
A good developer is the one with good critical thinking.
Yeah.
Where they can sit down and say, wait a second.
You know, I'll be honest about it.
I go into companies and I seriously ask them,
can you explain to me why you are doing this?
And you would be surprised at times when no one
they have literally committed
$2 million for a project, but nobody is able to tell you
why they need to implement the $2 million solution.
And to me that is the key.
If that doesn't change now, that's just as important before
and after more important now. Yeah, right.
Because a speed at which we are going is much faster now.
And if we forget to ask that why we're going to crash and burn with the
with the huge expenses moving forward, I think that question,
the why question is even more critical now than before, I think.
And if we don't train ourselves so so a good developer
needs critical thinking, a good developer needs courage.
You know, I feel intimidated, right?
Because, hey, I'm sitting next to a, you know, good developer,
but I need to say, excuse me, can you give me why?
And that person is good.
I mean, you know, I'm a consultant. I go to companies.
I remember one experience.
I was in a company that was reimplemented their software
to a newer, more modern language, and they had a feature
and and the president of the there was a smaller company.
The person president of the company
is sitting in the meeting and everybody else is there.
And they were talking about a feature.
I'm the consultant.
I don't know anything about their product.
These are people who have been working with the product for a long time.
And I said, can you tell me why you're implementing this feature?
Oh, the current version has it.
So we need to implement it because we just modernizing the application.
Thank you.
Can somebody in the room explain to me why you are doing this?
As I just said, the product has this feature
when it implement it like no, no, no I heard your explanation.
Let's go past it.
Why are we implementing this feature?
And a few people said a few things and one guy got really angry.
What part of.
It's there already and we need it
doesn't reach you.
I'm like, oh my gosh, that's really rude.
And if you don't want to answer, just tell me you don't know.
That's fine.
And we were kind of going back and forth with this.
And suddenly the president of the company who was in the room got up and said,
all right, I want somebody in the room to answer that question.
So now the boss wants the answer, right?
And everybody is quiet.
Nobody could answer it.
And he then said, who in this room. No.
That 60% of support call
we are getting is on that feature.
And I'm like, definitely.
I don't know that because I'm new to your company and everybody's like,
oh, he was like, yep, 60% of the call is coming from the feature
from that feature, and nobody in the room ever questioned it.
And now that that question has come up.
It just dawned on me it shouldn't even be here.
I know exactly how to take care of that need outside,
and all of a sudden we don't have that 60% of the problem we are having.
So he walked up, put a little rectangle around it, crossed it, and said,
this will not be in the new product to me again, right?
I am not the best person in the world, not the smartest person in the world.
But to me, if I don't understand why
I am the stubbornness person on your team, I'm going to keep insisting.
I'm sorry, but tell me why.
I'm to play devil's advocate.
Why couldn't why didn't.
AI pose those questions and try and answer them?
AI may not be capable to post that question,
but AI will answer those questions if you ask.
So you hit on something that I've been fascinated by for the past
20 years, and I think this only became
more interesting when, when I was a kid,
I had to know the answers.
You know, my children always are fascinated.
They look at me and say, dad, what do you mean?
There was no internet when you were a kid and there was no Google.
There was no there was no browser when I was a kid,
and I had to know the answers.
All of a sudden for the past 20 years,
I had to know the questions and not the answers.
If I don't know the right question and again,
you know, this is what surprises me.
People will come and ask me the question, and how do I do this?
I'll give them an answer by just doing a search.
And I always think, why am I able to certain?
Why do they search?
Because they didn't know how to ask the question.
With AI,
it's even more
critical we know how to ask the right question.
So if you were asking the right question,
you're saying, hey, you, you created this for me.
Thank you.
Why are we creating it this way?
Why are we even solving this problem?
Can you tell me what are the risks in the solution you just created?
If you are able to ask those questions,
AI has those answers.
It just doesn't tell you.
Yeah, because it's not thinking of those questions.
And another, maybe a better way
of using AI today in this kind of sense is to have.
Because I always think AI is great when it's almost critiquing
and like having AI.
Maybe I'll create a venture agent that asks me why,
and asks me these types of questions to understand and makes me think,
you know,
forces me to to learn this muscle of why are we building this?
I would rather have assignment agent. Said.
That is going to be really buggy.
I tell you that right away.
It'll be more polite.
Banker.
Let's jump into some quick fire questions.
All right, so, Venkat, what's the conversation you most want
developers to be having right now that they're not having.
The most important conversation
I think developers should have is
how can we be more sustainable
in developing products
where we can deliver value while reducing the risk
and creating the financial success for companies?
You know, oftentimes I ask questions as people, you walk into a company,
why are you here? What value do you produce today?
If I cannot answer that question, I'm in the wrong place.
Yeah. So I think that's that's what I want people to know.
How can you make your your efforts sustainable.
Tests first or vibe in iterate.
That was the easiest easy.
That was easy. Feedback loops.
If I you know,
I was thinking about it this morning, honestly, if I don't know where I'm going.
It doesn't matter where I end up.
Test gives me the direction.
What's one thing AI will never replace in a good developer?
The passion for what we create.
Nice.
What is the most overrated AI trend right now?
Vibe coding.
What's the most underrated AI trend right now?
Seriously, I would say it's ability
to really identify issues and analyze risk.
I wish we are talking more about it
and not more about where it's not good.
Let's spend more time focusing on what it's good at.
I think we wish.
I wish we did that more. Yeah.
Nice.
Then, as an author of I can't remember how many, let's say a thousand.
Let's round it to a thousand books.
What is a book that every AI native developer should read
that has nothing to do with AI?
Wow. I'm going to
talk about a book I've read a few times.
One of my favorite books.
Because every one of us needs
to clear our mind from time to time.
So the one I recommend always is who moved the cheese?
Who moved the cheese?
A great book.
Such a good book. Awesome. Thank you.
This has been an absolute pleasure.
And to to.
I've actually, to be honest, wanted you in the podcast for a long time
and to to record the episode here at the arc of AI conference in Austin.
It's been absolutely amazing.
It's been wonderful, wonderful to do that. Thanks for joining.
Thanks for making this a very good event.
And I enjoyed and I can tell you how appreciated.
By an amazing.
And actually to those listeners, I would say arc of
AI is probably the the AI conference
that has among the highest quality of sessions and speakers.
And attendees. And attendees.
Hands down the conversation.
Actually, when I, when I when I got here and started
chatting to people, I was starting to get worried, thinking.
Am I is my is my level too low to to high level for people here?
Luckily I think I'm at a good level.
But yeah, the quality of attendees is very, very strong.
So put it in the calendar for next year.
Arc of AI in Austin, US.
Definitely one for your list to to attend.
Venkat, it's been an absolute pleasure.
Let's go enjoy the rest of Arc of AI.
Thank you. Simon. Thank you. Thank you so much.
Thanks very much for listening and tune in to the next episode soon.
Bye for now.
native dev is brought to you by the package manager for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI native dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit Tessl.io/community to learn more and I hope to see you there.